BUKHALA SOLOMON. S. MAROBOLO P. O. Box 46656-00100, Nairobi

Cell: +254-722229314

Email: solomonbukhala@gmail.com

PERSONAL

Nationality: Kenyan, DOB: 27/8/1958, Marital status: Married, Religion: Christian,

Language: English, Kiswahili & Braille.

Objective: To be a leader in Project Planning & Management of projects and programs.

Identification, Appraisal, Financing, Implementation & evaluation of projects and programs with the ultimate objective of improving lives of people in communities.

EDUCATION

ACADEMIC COURSEWORK

INSTITUTION QUALIFICATION DURATION

- University of Nairobi: MA PPM (Masters of Arts in Project Planning & Management-2013- 2016
- Kenyatta University B.Ed. (Special Education: Honors Upper second class-1995-1998
- Private Candidate: K.A.C.E (Kenya Advanced certificate of education)- Pass- 1983
- Musingu High School: (E.A.C.E) East African Certificate of Education, Division 2-1974-1977.
- Kenya Institute of Special Education (KISE): 1985-1987
 Diploma in Special Education (Education for the persons with visual impairment)
- EGOJI TEACHER TRAINING COLLEGE -1979- 1981

PTE-Primary Teaching Certificate (PI)

PROFESSIONAL

PROFILE

A seasoned professional with 35 years of work experience in Education & Program Coordination

Possess hands on experience in Education policies, Habilitation & Rehabilitation of persons with visual impairment, resource management, team consensus, developing budgets & continuous improvement strategist. Motivated with current digital explosion and management challenges and desire to be successful in all endeavors.

Key competencies:

Proven teaching & leadership skills

- Efficient and Effective leader, mentor & counselor.
- Communication, public speaking & writing skills.
- Capacity in Research & policy analysis
- Decision maker and with strong Negotiating abilities and exceptional ability to resolve conflicts.
- Skills and knowledge on the project cycle; planning and budgeting, implementation,
 Evaluation.
- Competent in budgeting and reporting of projects funded by international partners
- Excellent at partnerships, networking and collaboration.
- Proficiency in developing organizational strategy & policy documents.
- Competent in rehabilitation of persons with visual impairment.
- Resilient and never gives up despite of the challenges.

SELECTED PROFESSIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

- A member of the Technical Committee of Special Education at the Kenya Bureau of Standards from 2010 to date.
- A member of Disability Mainstreaming committee at the Ministry of Education from 2010 to 2014.
- Secretary of the Working Task force on establishment of Braille Authority of Kenya
 2014 to date.
- Chaired a sub-committee on Assistive devices for Persons with visual impairment at the National Council for Persons with Disabilities that developed a glossary for specified Assistive devices for persons with visual in January 2013.
- Led a team that successfully worked on the action plan that established a department of Special Needs Education at the Directorate of Secondary and Tertiary at Ministry of Education in 2013.
- Has a recognition of spearheading Kenya Integrated Education Program as the best inclusive Education program funded by Sight savers and led a team of beneficiaries to UK in 2010 during the midterm review of MDGs.
- Participated and presented the Kenyan Experience of good practices on inclusive education in Cameroun Yaoundé during the formation of Cameroun Inclusive Program in Oct, 2012.

- Participated in the development of the Ministry of Education Special Needs Education policy in 2010.
- Spearheaded mainstreaming of Kenya Integrated Education Program activities within the Ministry of Education District Educational, Assessment and Resource Centers (DEARCs) for sustenance.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Program Planning & Management,
- Monitoring and Evaluation.
- Financial analysis and budgeting.
- Strategic planning.
- Resource Mobilization.
- Lobbying and Advocacy
- Partnership and Networking.
- Mainstreaming education for learners with visual impairment.
- Habilitation and Rehabilitation of persons with visual Impairment

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

KENYA SOCIETY FOR THE BLIND, NAIROBI JAN 2009-PRESENT

Position: Education and Rehabilitation Services Manager

- Coordinates and implements education activities for Learners with visual impairment
- Sensitizes and raises awareness on inclusive education approaches.
- Demystifies mainstreaming of disability in agencies, government departments and other organizations
- Develops all budgets and plans for Education and Rehabilitation program at Kenya Society for the Blind including donor funds
- Prepares Performance Contracts & Performance Development Reviews for all personnel in Education and Rehabilitation programs.
- Develops detailed annual implementation plans for Education and Rehabilitation program at KSB
- Ensures timely quarterly and annual quality donor reports
- Has gained recognition for developing concepts that have enabled Kenya Society for the Blind to link and work with universities and County governments.
- Oversees habilitation and rehabilitation of persons with visual impairment at the Kenya Society for the Blind.

Management of team work and member of management team.

NAIROBI INTEGRATED EDUCATION PROGRAM, 2002-2008

Position: National Program Coordinator,

- Developed structures for Nairobi program that were approved by the Ministry of Education that include board of management, registration of statutory deductions for all staffs and establishment of four resource centers in Nairobi.
- Developed partner's agreements that enhanced funding
- Sensitized and raised awareness on inclusion of LWVI in regular schools in Nairobi.
- Hosted stakeholders meetings that enhanced enrollment of LWVI in schools.
- Gained recognition having influenced LWVI from other counties to be admitted in schools in Nairobi.
- Ensured formation of parents support groups
- An advocate of child protection in Nairobi Integrated Education program supported by CBM
- Maintained inventories of all procured and distributed learning and teaching materials.
- Ensured all learners with visual impairment attained minimum standard of requirements
- Equipped parents with learners with visual impairment with braille skills, Orientation and mobility and ADL skills.
- Built the capacity of Itinerant teachers in vision screening procedures.
- Sensitized most teachers in regular schools about integrated education.
- Gained recognition of creating more sensitization forums for education officers and school Managers
- Hosted several media events that made Kilimani Primary to be recognized as a Centre of excellence for inclusion in Nairobi.
- Nairobi Integrated Education program developed into a role model program during my tenure.

WEST POKOT EARC, 1998-2002

Position: District Coordinator of Educational Assessment & Resource Services. (DEARCS)

- Coordinated Distance Learning for Kenya Institute for Special Education for both certificate and Diploma teachers training.
- Enhanced assessment by adopting multidisciplinary approach that operated at the Centre twice in a week.
- Gained recognition for keeping the Assessment Centre operational throughout the week.
- Established parents support groups and equipped members with identification and referral skills.
- Inducted local provincial administration in identification and referral procedures of persons with disability
- Recognized for having gained support from churches in conducting screening and follow up.

ST. FRANCIS SCHOOL FOR THE BLIND-1987-1995

Position: - Special Teacher for the Visually Impaired

- Inducted teachers within the school in O/M skills.
- Ensured that all Learners With Visual Impairment were independent and able to use white cane confidently
- Conducted braille lessons to all teachers who had not trained in Braille
- In charge of examinations within the school
- National examiner in Braille center at Moi Nairobi Girls during KCPE marking.
- Repaired and maintained Braille machines within the school and in the rest of North Rift.
- In charge of adapted sports and games within the school
- Represented the school in all forums of sports and games for LWVI.
- Two learners with visual impairment competed in Barcelona –Spain during the Olympics
- Trained LWVI on how to use the abacus, cubes and cuberithms boards, Taylor frames and Types
- In charge of braille literacy and braille books production

UASIN GISHU DISTRICT-1983-1985

Position: Deputy Head teacher- Cerengoni Primary

- In charge of school Discipline
- In charge of the school Time table
- In charge of school stores
- In charge of staff minutes
- Holding briefs for the Head teacher

Uasin Gishu District: 1981-1982

Position: Assistant Teacher

- National examiner during KCPE marking
- Mathematics teacher in upper Primary
- Music Teacher
- Games master

INTERESTS

- Reading
- Swimming
- Travelling

REFERENCES

- Jackson Musungu, Senior Assistant Director of Education, Ministry of Education, Directorate of Basic Education, Box 30426-00100, Nairobi. Email. jackson.musungu@yahoo.com. 0720237855. My relationship with him is professional.
- 2) Dr. Bernard Mogesa, Principal Human Rights Officer, Kenya National Commission on Human Rights, Email: bmogesa@knchr.org. 0720966637. He is my mentor in my current assignment.